Alba Refoyo-Martínez

Driven by curiosity and a strong sense of organization, I develop reproducible pipelines, create containerised environments, and apply advanced modelling to tackle challenges in omics and health data. With 6+ years of bioinformatics expertise, I focus on meaningful insights through efficiency, reproducibility, and FAIR principles. I'm seeking an inspiring role where I can contribute meaningfully while continuing to grow, innovate, and challenge myself.

albarema@gmail.com

(+45) 91 92 54 85

Auroravei 10E st. 2610 Rødovre, DK LinkedIn: albarefoyo

albarema.github.io github.com/albarema

SKILLS

- Bioinformatics workflows & pipeline development
- Data analysis & visualization
- Data management
- · Omics data integration
- · Collaboration in crossdisciplinary groups
- Cloud computing & containerization

EXPERTISE

- Python & R
- Docker & Conda
- Snakemake & Nextflow
- nf-core
- · Git & GitHub
- Shiny

PERSONAL QUALITIES

- Motivated by challenges
- Proactive learner
- Highly organized
- Analytical
- Independent
- **Decision-making**
- Positive

LANGUAGES

 English: proficiency Spanish: native

· Danish: beginner

VOLUNTEERING

- · Conference chair, **Evolutionary and Population** Genetics in Denmark - EPIC 2023
- · Conference organizer, **Evolutionary and Population** Genetics in Denmark - EPIC 2022
- · Member, Globe PhD Committee

EXPERIENCE

University of Copenhagen

Data scientist

Section for Health Data Science and AI, Public Health

Feb 2024 - Present

- Developed and deployed containerised training modules on Danish HPC systems for
- Designed toolkits for efficient research data management (RDM)
- Optimised workflows for large-scale omics pipelines
- · Delivered workshops on containerisation, HPC, scalable and reproducible workflows, and data science practices
- · Maintained version-controlled GitHub repositories and managed project documentation using Quarto

Postdoctoral researcher

Section for Molecular Ecology and Evolution, Globe Institute

Nov 2022 - Jan 2024

- Developed and optimised computational pipelines for processing omics data
- Implemented novel computational tools tailored to specific research inquiries
- Conducted genetic modelling in collaboration with Variant Bio to explore genetic variation and disease mechanisms.

PhD student

Lundbeck Foundation Geogenetics Centre, Globe Institute Oct 2019 - Oct 2022 Department of Integrative Biology at University of California, Berkeley Sep 2022 - Oct 2022

- Developed computational pipelines for genomic data analysis
- Utilised whole-genome sequence data to predict genetic disease risk
- Performed data visualization of complex time-series genomic data

Graduate researcher

Apr 2018 - Sep 2019

 Developed R-based software to identify genetic selection signatures in next-generation sequencing (NGS) data

EDUCATION

Doctor in Philosophy (DPhil), Bioinformatics University of Copenhagen Change of research environment

Master of Science (MSc) in Bioinformatics Elective student

Bachelor of Science (BSc) in Health Biology Erasmus program

2019-2022 University of California, Berkeley Sep. 2022

University of Copenhagen 2017-2019 Copenhagen Business School

Universidad de Alcalá 2013-2017 Vrije Universiteit Brussel 2016-2017

SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

I have contributed to numerous high-impact publications and developed my communication skills by presenting at global conferences. Check My Google Scholar to see the list of publications.